字幕转制｜天外生物
感谢原字幕制作者
领衔主演
伯特·兰卡斯特
导演
鲁奇诺·维斯康蒂
豹
主演
克劳狄娅·卡迪纳莱
阿兰·德龙
圣母玛利亚，上帝与你同在…
Hail Mary, full of grace, the Lord be with thee...
外面为何那么吵？
What is that disturbance?
发生什么事了？
What has happened?
殿下，花园里发现一名士兵的尸体
Excuse me, Your Excellency. A dead soldier has been found in the garden.
什么？
What?
整座城市都在动乱
There's rioting in the city, everywhere.
这封信是刚送来的…
This letter has arrived.
梅维卡公爵的来信，万分火急
It's urgent. From the Duke of Malvica.
“亲爱的法里兹奥，看看报纸上可怕的消息”
"Dear Fabrizio, read the terrible news in the paper."
“皮埃蒙特人登陆了，我们失守了”
"The Piedmontese have landed. We are lost."
“我们全家今晚乘英国战船逃难”
"My family and I are taking refuge in the English ships anchored here."
“你可能也要赶紧逃”
"I'm sure you'll do likewise."
“愿主保佑我们的国王…”
"God save our beloved king."
懦夫！
The coward!
“五月十一日，武装分子登陆马沙拉…”
"An act of piracy was committed on 11th May..."
“将公然的侵略活动推向高潮”
...when armed men landed at Marsala."
“武装分子约有八百人，由加里波第率领”
"Reports say there were about 800, led by Garibaldi."
“他们避开了与皇家军队的正面遭遇…”
"The brigands carefully avoided any clash with royalist troops..."
“向卡斯特尔韦特拉诺进发…”
"...and made for Castelvetrano..."
“沿路胁迫居民，掠夺财产，肆意破坏”
"...threatening peaceful inhabitants and causing pillage and devastation."
保罗，你们今晚搬去马勒莫的宫殿，房子一空就会沦陷的
Paolo, you'll go to the house in Palermo. Empty houses are lost houses.
法里兹奥，这样太危险了，要打仗了！
No, please, Fabrizio. It's dangerous. This is war.
保罗，把米米找来
Francesco Paolo, call Mimi.
这是革命
It's the revolution.
喝了这个你会好点的
Drink this, you'll feel better.
他来了，爸爸
He's just coming, father.
对不起，殿下，我们在花园里发现了…
Pardon, Excellency. In the garden we've found...
米米，让安东尼奥备好马车，快去
Mimi, tell Don Antonio to harness the horses to the carriage.
吃完饭我要去巴勒莫
I'll go to Palermo after our meal.
皮诺神父…
Father Pirrone...
你跟我一起去，好吗？
...you'll accompany me, won't you?
愿上帝保佑我们
May the Lord protect us.
街上全是士兵…
But with the streets full of soldiers, bandits...
你能和耶稣教友们聚上几个小时，我们十一点回去
You'll spend two hours with your colleagues. We'll return at eleven.
半小时内吃饭
We eat in half an hour.
所有人都吃
All of you.
我们还能做什么？
What are we going to do?
救救我们，仁慈的圣母…
Save us, Queen of Heaven, mother of mercies...
这些坏蛋死后还是这么臭
These swines stink even when they're dead.
塞尔瓦托，你报告兵营那边了吗？
Salvatore, did you alert the barracks?
殿下，兵营派他们来把尸体抬走
Excellency, we've told them to come and remove him.
殿下，时局动荡啊
What terrible times, Excellency.
看看山上的战火
Look at all the fires on the mountains.
☆叛军的营地★我看见了，神父
☆They're the rebels' camps.★I see them, Father.
也许殿下是在担心塔克罗迪
Perhaps Your Excellency is worried about Don Tancredi.
他应该提防一下他那些狐朋狗友…
Tancredi should guard against certain friendships...
对他们多留一份戒心
...certain dangerous acquaintances.
不该怪他，社会环境使然！
Father, the fault is not Tancredi's. The fault is the times.
如今，出身名门的年轻人难免会交到些狐朋狗友
A young nobleman cannot even play cards without making dangerous friends.
够了
That's enough now.
不过还是该小心谨慎…
Still, a little prudence...
停车，爱罗迪别墅关卡检查
Halt! Villa Airoldi road-block.
晚上好，殿下，请见谅
Good evening Your Excellency. Excuse us.
给萨利纳王子殿下放行
Let the Prince of Salina through.
倘若没有那么多耶稣会士…
What a beautiful country this would be if...
我们国家将多么美好
If there weren't so many Jesuits.
十点钟我来接你，好好祈祷，神父
I'll come back for you in two hours. Pray well, Father.
☆我们去哪？★港口边的酒馆
☆Where can we go?★To the tavern, by the port.
晚上好，美男子
Good evening, handsome.
梅琳娜，他不适合你
Melina, that's not for you.
你少管闲事
Mind your own business.
殿下
My big prince.
早上好，舅舅
Good day, uncle.
塔克罗迪，你昨晚去哪儿了？
Tancredi. What were you up to last night?
没去哪儿，舅舅
Nothing at all, uncle.
我和几个朋友出去了，没干什么
I was with friends, a virtuous night.
我才不像某些人去巴勒莫…
Not like some I know, who went to amuse themselves...
寻欢作乐
...down in Palermo.
你说谁呢？
And who would they be?
你啊，舅舅
You yourself, uncle.
我亲眼看到你在爱罗迪别墅…
I saw you talking to the sergeant at the road-block.
与哨站的警官说话
A fine thing, at your age.
还带了个神父一起
And with a reverend father, too.
你这个花花公子
Such libertines.
我想是吧
Well, after all, it's true.
干嘛穿成这样？去参加舞会吗？
Why are you dressed like that? For a masked ball in the morning?
我一小时后就走，我是来道别的
I'm going soon, uncle. I came to say farewell.
怎么？你要去哪儿？不是去决斗吧？
Why? Where are you going? Not a duel...
没错，和国王作生死决斗
Yes. A great duel, uncle, with the king.
我要去法古扎山
I'm going to the mountains, to Ficuzza.
伟大事业正在酝酿，我可不想呆在家里
Great things are beginning and I don't want to stay at home.
总之，呆在家里我早晚被逮
They'd seize me here, anyway.
你简直疯了，那些人全是一群乌合之众
You are mad to join them. They're mafiosi, all swindlers.
法康利人应该与我们一起支持国王
A Falconeri should be with us, for the king.
支持国王，没错
Certainly, for the king.
但是哪个国王？你说过很多次了
But which king? You've said it yourself, uncle.
费迪纳德活着的话，哪会轮到小弗朗西斯？
If King Ferdinando were still alive... But Franceschiello? No, uncle.
你认为自诩为“绅士”的皮埃蒙特人更有治国之道？
You think the Piedmont man they call "The Gentleman" will be much better?
只不过将都灵方言换成那不勒斯方言而已
A Turin dialect instead of Neapolitan, that's all.
那你喜欢马兹尼共和国吗？
Then what about the republic of Peppino Mazzini?
不行动的话，他们就将共和政体强加于人
If we weren't here, that lot would soon foist the republic on you.
万物要保持永恒，就必须作出改变
If we want everything to remain as it is, everything has to change.
你明白吗？
Have I explained it?
再见，我会带着三色旗回来的
Good-bye, uncle. I'll return with the tricolour.
三色旗！你简直是一派胡言
The tricolour! You soil your lips with that word.
跟我们的金百合国旗比起来，三色旗算什么？
What is it compared with our golden lily banner?
那难看的颜色能给你什么希望？
What do you hope to gain from those colours?
舅舅，你这是自欺欺人
Wait, uncle, you're deluding yourself.
再见，舅舅
Good-bye, uncle.
再见
I'll see you soon.
等等，塔克罗迪！
Tancredi! Wait!
你这是干嘛？当作支持革命吗？
What are you doing? Subsidising the revolution now?
谢谢你了，舅舅
Thank you very much, uncle.
替我向舅妈问好
Kiss my aunt for me.
康塞塔，我很快就回来的
Concetta, I'll be back soon.
殿下来这里忏悔吗？
Has Your Excellency come for confession?
忏悔？今天不是星期天
Confession? It's not Saturday.
殿下，听我的话，忏悔吧
Excellency, listen to me. Make confession.
没这个必要，神父，你都知道的了
Father, there is no need. You know everything already.
忏悔不仅是说出我们的罪过，而且要将其改正
Confession is not the telling of facts, but the repentance of sins.
我知道
I know!
你要我怎样？我是个精力旺盛的男人
What do you expect of me? I'm a vigorous man.
一个每次拥抱前都要在胸口画十字，事后只会说“圣母玛莉亚”的女人…
Can I be content with a woman who in bed crosses herself before an embrace?
是不能给我任何满足感的
And who afterwards can only say: "Jesus Mary".
我跟她生了七个孩子…
I've had seven children by her...seven.
却从没见过她的肚脐！
And, Father, I've never seen her navel.
这公平吗？
Is that fair?
神父，她才是罪人
Is it, Father? She is the sinner.
殿下，我说话直来直去
I was too brusque.
在我面前请注意自己言行
Do not lose your goodwill towards me.
听我的劝告，来忏悔吧
But listen to me: confess.
我不想忏悔
I haven't any intention of confessing.
至少今天不想
At least, not today.
我发现了重大的政治问题
I've made some important political discoveries.
你知道国家在发生什么事吗？没什么
Do you know what's happening in our country? Nothing.
只不过是细微的阶级更替
A barely noticeable substitution of ruling groups.
中产阶级不想消灭我们，他们想取而代之
The middle class doesn't want to destroy us, but to take our place...
而且还慷慨地给我们一笔钱
...more politely, and even put thousands of ducats into our pockets.
然后，一切皆回复平常
And then the rest can stay as it is.
神父，国家的命运危在旦夕
Father, ours is a country of compromises.
你们贵族会以牺牲宗教为代价…
In short, you nobles will come to an agreement with the liberals...
与自由党人…
...even with the Masons...
甚至与共济会达成协议
...at our expense. Yes, at the expense of the church...
我们的财产…
...because it's clear that all our wealth...
也就是穷人的收入来源都会被叛党头目掠夺瓜分
...the patrimony of the poor, will be divided among the insolent ringleaders.
到时，宗教救济的贫苦大众要靠什么来维生？
Who then will feed the unhappy people whom the church still supports?
怎么安抚这些无法无天的叛党？
What will be done to placate that desperate horde?
先让他们一点点占有你的财产，直至完全占有
They will be given one piece of your land, then another, finally all of it.
眼睛失明，上帝能治愈…可心灵失明要靠什么拯救？
Our Lord healed the physically blind, but what about the mentally blind?
神父，我们的心灵并没有失明
We're not mentally blind, dear Father.
我们只是乱世中的凡人
Just human beings in a world of radical change.
我们能做什么？
What must we do?
宗教永垂不朽
The church has been given an explicit promise of immortality.
我们作为一个社会阶级不会永垂不朽
We, as a social class, have not.
说我们会长命百岁，只不过是种慰藉
A palliative that promises us another hundred years is the same as eternity.
在力所能及的范围之外，我们不需承担责任
Beyond what we can caress with our hands we have no obligations.
但宗教有责任，因为宗教是不朽的
The church must have obligations, because it is destined not to die.
宗教给人们含蓄的安慰
In its disappearance there might be some solace.
宗教如果靠牺牲我们…
Do you believe, Father, that if one day the church...
得以拯救自己的话…
...could save itself by sacrificing us it would hesitate to do so?
你以为它不会这样做吗？
It wouldn't hesitate, and it would do well.
星期天，你要为两项罪过忏悔
You'll have two sins to confess to me on Saturday.
一是昨晚的寻欢作乐，二是你今天的想法
A carnal sin last night and a spiritual one today.
看，神父，多美啊！
Look, Father, how beautiful.
单凭维克多·伊曼纽国王是改变不了这奇妙世界的
It will take more than King Victor Emmanuel to change this magic view.
加里波第军万岁！
Long live Garibaldi's men!
救救我！
Help me!
☆他是个警察，是凶手！★他罪有应得
☆He's a policeman, a murderer!★We dealt with him ourselves!
骑兵队来了
The cavalry!
先别急着开火！
Hold your fire!
冲啊，弟兄们！
Platoons, forward march!
护士小姐，快过来！
Hey, nurse, come here!
敌人往哪边跑了？
Where have they gone?
已经到港口了
By now they'll be at the port.
你有什么看法，神父？
What do you say, Father?
新时代会让我们过得更好吗？
Will these glorious new times give us better roads?
政府…
Well, the government...
让开！我们过不去！
Clear the road!
谁也不准过去，路被封了
Nobody can pass. It's blocked.
往比萨奇诺的路被封了
The road to Bisaquino is closed.
抱歉，这里严禁通过，你们不能再往前走了
I'm sorry, it's forbidden to pass. You can't go any further.
通行证也不行吗？
Evidently our permit is no good.
我可没这么说，所有平民的通行证都要暂缓
I'm not saying that. We've been told all civilian permits are suspended.
我让你回去，你就得回去！
If I tell you to turn back, you have to turn back!
把路障挪开，让马车过去
Clear the road so the carriages can proceed.
谁也不准过去！
Nobody gets through here!
我是塔克罗迪王子，和你们在巴勒莫并肩作战过！
I'm Captain Prince Tancredi Falconari. I fought at Palermo with you.
我有权下军令！
Captain, I have my orders.
这也是军令，快把路障撤走！
This is an order, too. Clear the way!
你和贵族住在一起
You live among the nobility.
他们对革命有什么看法？
What do they say about this huge conflagration?
那位暴躁而自大的萨利纳王子怎么说？
What does our fierce, proud Prince of Salina say?
你所说的贵族很难捉摸
The nobility, as you call them, aren't easy to understand.
他们所生活的那个世界…
They live in a world apart, not created by God...
是他们用经历了数个世纪的…
...but by themselves, during centuries of very special experiences...
烦恼和喜悦创造出来的
...of troubles and joys★their joys.
那些你我觉得微不足道的事情…
They get upset or are fascinated by things that to you and me...
对他们却至关重要…
...don't matter at all, but which for them are vital.
我并非说他们是坏人，完全不是
I don't mean the nobles are bad, on the contrary.
他们与众不同
They're different.
我们认为重要的事，他们不会在意…
They don't care about certain things which are very important to us...
我们觉得无所谓的事，他们反而担心
...and maybe they have fears we're ignorant of.
比如说，在萨利纳王子看来…
The Prince of Salina, for example.
若赶不去杜纳福卡特度假，那简直是个悲剧
He couldn't give up his holiday in Donnafugata. That's where we're going.
但要是问他如何看待革命…
But if you ask him what he thinks, of the revolution...
他会说并没有革命，一切依然如故
...he says there's no revolution, everything will go on as before.
但愿如此吧
That's the last straw.
我们还是来看祈祷书吧
Let's read the breviary. It's better.
我来看看…
Let's see...
《旧约·诗篇》第四十四篇
Psalm 45.
“我的心激情澎湃，我做的事让君主动容”
My heart overfloweth, I speak of the things I have made touching the king.
“我的舌头犹如作家手中之笔”
My tongue is the pen of a ready writer.
“你比世人更美”
Thou art fairer than the children of men.
“在你嘴里满有恩惠，神永远赐福予你”
Grace is poured into thy lips, God hath blessed thee for ever.
快点
Quickly, lads.
铺好点，你去拿酒，你拿酒杯
Spread it neatly. You fetch the bottles, and you the glasses.
希望一切能合您的心意
We hope that everything is just as you want it.
很高兴又和您见面了，殿下
I'm delighted to see you again, Excellency.
现在我们稍作休息
Now we'll just rest a little.
你们可在树下用餐
You can eat beneath the trees.
一小时后继续赶赴杜纳福卡特，那些士兵经过这儿吗？
We'll leave for Donnafugata in an hour. Tell me about the soldiers...
这里比阿尔及利亚更糟
It's worse than in Algeria.
这里和阿尔及利亚不同，亲爱的
It's different from Algeria, my dear.
你不想梳洗一番吗？
Wouldn't you like to refresh yourself?
把额头和太阳穴擦擦
Try bathing your temples.
我们快去吃饭吧，不然就没东西吃了
Let's join the others, or we'll find nothing left to eat.
你饿吗？
Aren't you hungry?
我跟大家说：“殿下今年不会离开巴勒莫”
I told everyone: "His Excellency won't leave Palermo this year."
“时局如此动乱，怎么能旅游呢？”
"How do you expect them to travel in times like these?"
“殿下及其家人发生了何事？”
"Who knows what will happen to His Excellency? May God protect him!"
不过你们都安然无恙
But you're all safe and sound.
感谢上帝
I thank God.
你以为我们出什么事了？一切都很平常
What did you expect to happen to us? It was all very simple.
实际上，加里波第进入巴勒莫后不久…
In fact, a few days after Garibaldi's entry into Palermo...
塔克罗迪邀请一位托斯卡纳将军来家作客
...Tancredi brought home a nice Tuscan general...
将军想欣赏别墅里的壁画
...who wanted to admire the frescos at the villa...
还帮我们拿到了去杜纳福卡特的通行证
...and he proved useful in obtaining permits for Donnafugata.
将军能光临寒舍，我们深感荣幸
We are most happy to receive you in our home, General.
谢谢你，殿下
Thank you, Excellency.
他称呼你为殿下…这违反了加里波第的首条军规
He called you "Excellency". He's never broken Garibaldi's orders before.
将军，我外甥跟我说您想看看壁画
General, my nephew has told me that you would like to see the frescos.
☆是的，殿下★我们现在就看吧
☆Very much, Excellency.★Let's do it at once.
中间是朱庇特和朱诺，还有战神，爱神和墨丘利
In the centre, Jupiter and Juno, Mars, Venus and Mercury.
那边是海神和森林女神，接着是西蒂斯
On the other side, Tethys preceded by a group of tritons and dryads.
被云环绕的太阳神，所有这些都让萨利纳宫殿金壁生辉
Apollo surrounded by clouds, and all exalting the house of Salina's glory.
要薄荷糖吗？
Would you like another mint caramel?
谢谢，我最喜欢了
Thank you, they're just the sort I like.
我特地为你准备的
I brought them especially for you.
他脸色很苍白，伤得真不重吗？
How pale you are. Was your wound really not serious?
什么？
Pardon?
能够被提拔，受点伤也值得
It's worth being wounded to become promoted on the battlefield.
马车来了！
The carriages are coming!
欢迎您，殿下
I am happy to welcome your excellencies.
奥诺弗利奥，你还好吗？
Don Onofrio! How are we?
还好，我将把这里的宫殿…
Excellency, I hand you back the palace...
原封不动地交还于您
...in the exact state in which it was left.
能和巴勒莫受伤的英雄握手，我倍感荣幸
I am proud to shake the hand of the hero wounded fighting at Palermo.
受伤！我成为军官是因为有只虫子飞进了眼睛
Wounded? They made me a captain because I got a gnat in my eye.
卡洛吉罗，我知道你付出了很多
You've done much for the cause, Don Calogero.
克里斯彼对你赞誉有加
Crispi speaks very highly of you.
亲爱的特雷斯纳，再见到你真是太好了
Dear Teresina, what a pleasure to see you again.
还有你，有什么消息吗，希斯奥？
And you, of course, Don Ciccio. What news?
消息？我不大清楚，殿下
News? I haven't any, Excellency.
我先失陪一下
Will you excuse me now?
别忘了派今晚宴会的请柬，女士们都要来
Remember to invite them to dinner tonight, with their wives.
☆为什么？★这样最好
☆Why the wives?★It's better.
邀请卡洛吉罗，叫他携夫人出席
Invite Don Calogero and tell him to bring his wife.
公证人及其夫人
The lawyer with his wife.
还有希斯奥，还好他没有夫人
Don Ciccio, who thank God hasn't a wife.
请其他人晚餐后过来
All the others to come after dinner.
☆谁？★殿下，是我，米米
☆What is it?★It's Mimi, Excellency.
皮诺神父想即刻见您
Father Pirrone asks to see you at once.
好吧，让他进来
All right. Show him in.
对不起，殿下，我不知道你在沐浴
I beg your pardon, Excellency. I didn't know.
没关系，神父
Don't be shocked, Father.
你习惯面对赤裸的灵魂，赤裸的身体更加无罪
You're used to souls being bared. Bare bodies are much more innocent.
把毛巾拿给我
Just give me the towel.
别不好意思，神父
Go on, be brave, Father.
用点力，神父
Brisker, Father.
听我一句劝，偶尔自己洗一下澡
Take my advice: take a bath yourself now and then.
请坐
Take a seat, then.
这么急着见我有什么事？
Tell me why you wanted to talk to me so urgently.
有人委以我一个很棘手的任务
I have been entrusted with a very delicate mission.
您的一位宝贝向我吐露心声
A person very dear to you wanted to open her heart to me, to tell you...
看在您对我关心的份上，让我告诉你…
She has faith, perhaps mistaken, in the esteem with which you honour me.
不要拐弯抹角的
Can't you be more concise?
你说的是谁？是王妃吗？
Who are you referring to? The Princess?
不是，殿下，王妃很累，她正在休息
No, Excellency. The Princess is very tired and she is resting now.
是康塞塔小姐
It concerns signorina Concetta.
她堕入情网了
She is in love.
康塞塔？到底怎么回事？
Signorina Concetta? But how...
胡说
Oh, such foolishness.
对不起，让您担心了
I regret having disturbed you.
我觉得…
I did not think...
一个自认为很年轻的四十五岁人…
At forty-five a man may still think he's young...
当他意识到自己孩子已到了恋爱年龄时…
...until he realizes his children are old enough to fall in love.
突然之间，他就变得老了
Then old age suddenly comes crashing down on him.
你还没问康塞塔小姐喜欢上了哪个年轻人
You haven't asked me who the young man is, whom Concetta...
不用告诉我
There's no need.
傻孩子！她为何不亲自来告诉我？
Why didn't that stupid girl come to tell me?
你觉得我应该怎么说？
Well, in your opinion, what should I say?
教堂绝对支持建立基督教家庭
The desire to found a Christian family is most welcome to the church.
上帝对于婚姻…
The presence of Our Lord at the wedding in Cana...
别扯远了，神父，我说的是我女儿的婚姻
Let us not digress, Father. I intend to speak about this marriage...
不是宗教婚姻，也不是一般的婚姻
...not the wedding in Cana, nor marriage in general.
塔克罗迪有向她求婚吗？
Has Don Tancredi made a definite proposal? When?
没有正式求婚，殿下
Well, Excellency, not actually a proposal
但康塞塔小姐很坚定，他的一举一动，匆匆一瞥…
But Concetta has no doubts. His attentions, his looks...
他说的每句话，她确定他是爱她的
...certain words... she is sure he loves her...
觉得他很快就会向她求婚
...and feels he will propose at any moment.
别担心，神父，危险没那么快会来
Don't worry, Father, there's no immediate danger.
这些不过是女孩子的浪漫幻想
These are the fantasies of a romantic schoolgirl.
为什么说“危险”？
But why "danger", Excellency?
你能想像康塞塔成为维也纳或彼得堡的大使夫人吗
Can you imagine her as an ambassador's wife in Vienna, or St. Petersburg?
我喜欢康塞塔…
I love Concetta. I like her.
文静顺从
So placid, so submissive.
但塔克罗迪前途一片光明
But Tancredi has a great future before him.
她那么顺从害羞，又怎么能够…
How can Concetta, so passively virtuous, so shy and reserved...
帮助雄心勃勃的丈夫登上飞黄腾达的仕途？
...help an ambitious husband ascend the slippery steps of a new society?
塔克罗迪需要钱
Tancredi will find money useful.
康塞塔当然会有嫁妆
Concetta has her dowry, of course.
但我的家产要分成七份…
But the Salina fortune will have to be divided into seven parts.
远远不够塔克罗迪所需要的
I repeat, seven parts. Tancredi needs something else entirely.
苏特拉的女孩怎么样？
One of the Sutera girls, perhaps?
是，我知道，很普通，但却很有钱！
Yes, I know. They're so ugly, poor things, but so rich.
不过什么？爱情？
But what? Love?
当然了，一年的热情，随后是三十年的平淡
Of course, love. Fire and flame for one year, ashes for thirty.
爱情就是这么回事
I also know what love is.
殿下，您要穿哪套衣服去参加晚宴？
Excellency, which clothes will you wear for dinner?
神父，跟康塞塔说我没有生气
Father, you'll tell Concetta I'm not at all annoyed...
如果不全是幻想，我们迟点再讨论
...but we'll discuss it when we are sure it's not romantic fantasy.
穿午后服
What suit? One for evening wear.
爸爸，卡洛吉罗穿着燕尾服上楼来了！
Papa! Don Calogero's coming up the stairs★in tails!
这比马沙拉登陆更让人吃惊
This news has impressed you more than the landing at Marsala.
卡洛吉罗打着白领结，这是革命的象征
Don Calogero in white tie. The sign of the revolution on the march.
他穿着晚礼服，你们仔细看看
Yes, it's true, in tails. But look at them.
还有鞋子
And the shoes.
☆我妻子身体抱恙，她感冒了★真遗憾
☆My wife is unwell. A slight cold.★I'm very sorry.
我带了女儿安杰莉卡来，请见谅
I hope you will excuse me if my daughter Angelica comes in her place.
没关系，快请
But certainly. Come in.
上个月，她一直都在说，希望接受您的接见
For a month she's talked of the pleasure it would give her to come.
我记得那时她还小，是个可爱的小姑娘
I remember her well as a very pretty little girl.
很高兴能再见到她
We shall be happy to see her again.
我女儿马上就到，她还没打扮好
She will be here in a moment, she wasn't quite ready.
我们家离这里很近
Our house is just over the road, as you know.
我们等她来
Yes, Don Calogero. We'll wait for her.
正如我所言，教堂急需修葺
As I told you, the church is really in a sorry state.
真美
Lovely.
我的安杰莉卡
My Angelica.
好久不见，你越变越美了
I haven't seen you for so long. You have changed... and not for the worse.
安杰莉卡小姐，我们无比荣幸…
We are very fortunate, signorina Angelica...
能邀请到如此美人光顾寒舍
...to welcome such a lovely flower into our home.
希望你有机会能常来作客
I hope we shall have the pleasure of seeing you very often.
谢谢你，殿下，谢谢你一直那么关照我和我父亲
Thank you, Prince. You are as kind to me as you have always been to Papa.
你好吗，康塞塔小姐？
How do you do, signorina Concetta?
安杰莉卡，我们跟小时候不同了
Angelica, as children we were never so formal.
伯爵，请让我介绍小女给你认识
Your Grace, allow me to present my daughter Angelica.
请各位入席
Dinner is served.
传统的千层饼
Several layers, as tradition demands.
☆路上累吗？★不是很累
☆Was the journey very tiring?★Not unduly.
对不起，饭菜很快就端来
They haven't served you yet, I'm sorry.
☆那姑娘真漂亮★是的，康塞塔很漂亮
☆A beautiful daughter.★Yes, Concetta.
我那座正在建造的乡下小屋外观虽然简陋…
The villa I'm having built outside the village will be modest, but...
不过却很舒适
...very comfortable.
我们饿坏了，先喝口美味的汤
How hungry we are. A good thing we didn't start with soup.
令人难忘的日子
Unforgettable days, I tell you.
只有一句暗号：武器和武装部队
Only one word of command, from mouth to mouth: arms and soldiers.
将军已经意识到西西里岛的商业价值
The General realized that when Sicilians get going, they do it well.
为何加入加里波第的部队
Why did you join Garibaldi?
“加里波第唯一的愿望就是和你并肩作战”
"If Garibaldi is your brother-in-arms he wants only to fight at your side."
加里波第是这样说的，不过我没想过路途会那么艰辛
Those are his own words. I did not think it would be so strenuous.
晚上在吉比罗沙行军，我从没走过那么远的路
I've never walked so much. Oh, the night march to Gibilrossa...
你遇到比克肖人了？
Did you meet Bixio?
他们很坚决
What a determined man.
他们信念坚定，作战勇猛
All of them determined and extraordinary.
比克肖和拉玛沙人交战时，我刚好在场
The scene between Bixio and La Masa, at which I just happened to be present.
特米尼沦陷时，我也在那儿作了短暂停留
And I was briefly at the taking of Termini.
当时我真是大开了眼界
I enjoyed myself enormously, believe me.
最有意思的是五月二十八日
We had the biggest laugh on 28th May.
将军要在修道院部署一个岗哨
The General needed a lookout post in the Origlione monastery.
我们敲门，拍门，诅咒…但她们就是不开门
We knocked, we swore★nobody answered the door.
那是隐居的修道院
It was a convent for a closed order of nuns.
对了，神父…
By the way, Reverend...
我们明天要去柯贝拉院长的坟前作祷告
...tomorrow we'll pray at the tomb of the reverend mother Corbera.
好，那些修女…
Excellent. Those good nuns...
已经获知殿下即将驾到
...have already been informed to expect your excellencies.
她们都在准备恭迎您的大驾
They're in a flurry of preparation for your visit.
我们都是到这里的次日就去那儿的
We've never missed going there the day after our arrival.
后来怎么样了？
And then? What happened?
我来告诉你
I'll tell you.
塔索尼，阿尔吉格第，我和其他几个人…
Tassoni, Aldrighetti and I and someone else...
试图破门而入，但没有工具
...tried to break down the door, to no avail.
我们在附近的房子里找了根木梁
So we ran to get a beam from a shelled house nearby.
最后门被打开了
Finally, with an infernal din, the door gave way.
我们进去，看不到一个人
We entered. Everywhere was deserted.
突然，从修道院的走廊那边…
Suddenly we heard desperate twitterings...
传来一阵阵尖叫声
...from around the corner of a corridor.
修女们躲在礼拜堂里，在圣坛旁挤成一团
Taking refuge in the chapel, the nuns were piled up against the altar.
天知道她们为何害怕年轻小伙子
Who knows what they feared from those ten fed-up young lads.
她们穿着黑色长袍，又老又丑…
It was comic to see them, old and ugly as they were...
眼中充满恐惧，全都做好了…
...with their black habits, startled eyes, all ready and willing...
殉难的准备
...for martyrdom...
她们像狗一样呜咽
...whining like bitches.
这时候塔索尼喊道…
Our handsome Tassoni yelled:
“我们没时间，修女！等这里有新修女我们再回来”
"We've no time, sisters. We'll return when you've got us some young novices."
我们大笑不止
All the boys fell about laughing.
离开修道院后，我们便去和皇家军作战了
We left the disappointed nuns and went to fire on the king's troops.
十分钟后我就受伤了
Ten minutes later I was wounded.
真希望我当时也在场
How I wish I'd been there with you all.
如果你在那儿，我们就不用等新修女了
If you'd been there, there would have been no need to wait for novices.
塔克罗迪，这些下流故事可以说给告解神父听…
Tancredi. Such crude stories should be told to your confessor.
而不是在饭桌上说给年轻女士听
You do not tell them to young ladies at table.
至少我在场时就不行
At least, not when I am present.
他说得对，我会帮他
He's right, I agree, and I'll help him, too.
不得不承认，这有点不光彩
But it can't be denied he's a little ignoble.
亲爱的吉古嘉
Oh, the lovely Gigogin.
十五岁时，她献出了贞操
At fifteen she made love.
我心中充满欢喜
Take a step forward, darling of my heart.
十六岁时，她结婚了
At sixteen she got married.
走向前一步，我心爱的宝贝
Take a step forward, darling of my heart.
十七岁时离开了丈夫
At seventeen I left.
走向前一步，我心爱的宝贝
Take a step forward, darling of my heart.
意大利万岁，加里波第万岁！
Long live Italy! Long live Garibaldi!
别愁眉苦脸的，我们不是去参加葬礼
Don't be so sad, Father. We aren't following a funeral.
风太大了
The wind... this dreadful wind.
你应该感谢上帝，没有风，空气就会充满恶臭
Thank the Lord. Without wind the air would be fetid.
按照秩序来投票，先到者先投
You must vote in an orderly fashion. The first to arrive vote first.
杜纳福卡特公民选举
The Cavour of Donnafugata.
殿下，您能来我们万分荣幸
Excellency, this is a great honour for me.
不用，皮诺神父不是这里的居民
No. Father Pirrone is not resident here.
投票推迟几分钟
Voting is suspended for a few minutes.
殿下能否赏个薄面…
May I have the honour...
进房喝杯薄酒？
...of inviting you for modest refreshment?
喝白葡萄酒酒精度应该低点
I think the white will be lighter.
向波旁皇室致敬
A late homage to the Bourbon flag.
我今天不能喝酒，我的胃很痛
I really cannot drink today. I have a most aggravating stomach upset.
今天是个大日子，你的胃痛算得了什么！
That's of secondary importance on such a day.
谢谢，我从不喝酒
Thank you, I never drink.
很荣幸，谢谢你的招待
Don Calogero, for my part I accept with pleasure.
我想说几句…
I'd like to say a few words...
但殿下，心中的喜悦实在无以言表
...but great joys, Prince, are silent.
我心情十分激动
It is with great emotion that I perform this task.
请允许我在此宣布…
I have the very great honour...
杜纳福卡特公民投票的结果
...to announce the result of the plebiscite of our community.
一八六〇年十月二十二日晚上六点…
In the year 1860, 22nd October, in Donnafugata...
在杜纳福卡特
...at six p.m...
地方选举委员会…
...the municipal electoral committee met...
核查了城里所有选民…
...to examine the votes given in the plebiscite...
进行公民投票的结果
...by the population of this community.
西西里岛人民希望意大利团结统一…
The Sicilian people want Italy to be one and indivisible...
维克多·伊曼纽…
...with Victor Emmanuel...
作为意大利立宪制君主，他的合法后嗣继承王位
...as constitutional monarch, and his legitimate descendants.
所有选票都已统计完毕…
All the votes having been taken and due...
投票结果亦已经过详细审核…
All the votes having been taken and due scrutiny made...
现选举结果如下…
...the following results have been obtained.
登记选民：五百一十五人
Electors registered: 515.
实际投票：五百一十二票
Votes cast: 512.
赞成票：五百一十二票！
Voting YES: 512.
反对票：零票！
Voting NO: zero.
希斯奥，二十一号你投了什么票？
And you, Don Ciccio, how did you vote on the 21st?
你怕什么？这里没有其他人，只有风和猎犬
What are you afraid of? There's only us, the wind and the dogs.
你这样问毫无意义
Excuse me, but your question is pointless.
杜纳福卡特每个人都投了赞成票
You know very well everyone in Donnafugata votes YES.
甚至有人说是你建议大家这样投票
It's even said that you advised waverers to vote that way.
没错
That's very true.
你投了赞成票？
So you voted YES?
不，殿下，我投了反对票
No, Excellency. I voted NO.
一百次反对票！
No, a hundred times no.
我知道你跟我说过…
All right, I know what you told me.
必要性，团结，机遇，也许你是对的
For necessity, unity and opportunity. Perhaps you were right.
我不懂政治，所以我不插足政治
I don't understand politics and I leave these things to others.
但我希斯奥·杜梅是个老实人…
But Ciccio Tumeo is a gentleman.
是个卑微的画家，穷困潦倒，穿着破烂不堪的裤子…
A failed artist, poor and miserable, with worn-out trousers...
但我不会忘记所受的恩惠
...but I hadn't forgotten benefits received, you know that, Excellency.
你知道，是伊莉莎白女皇…
It was Queen Isabella, the Spanish one...
是卡拉布里亚的西班牙女公爵让我有机会学习…
...who then was Duchess of Calabria★she made me study...
让我活到现在…
...and allowed me to be where I am today...
让我成为教堂的风琴师，让我承蒙殿下您的庇护
...organist at the Holy Church, paid by the kindness of Your Excellency.
在物资匮乏的年代，我母亲向法院请愿…
In the years when our need was great, my mother sent an entreaty to Court...
结果得到了五盎司金币，这千真万确
...and financial assistance arrived, as sure as death.
如果现在那些国王皇后瞧不起我们，他们会怎么说？
If those kings and queens looked down from heaven, what would they say?
说里昂纳多·杜梅的儿子背叛了他们？不
That the son of Leonardo Tomeo betrayed them? No!
不会，殿下
No, Excellency.
幸运的是，没人知道真相！
Thank goodness, the truth is known in paradise.
我敬佩你的忠心和虔诚
I admire your loyalty and devotion.
但你得明白加里波第的胜利让人们过度兴奋
But understand that people are over- excited by this Garibaldi's victory.
当前，全民公投是治愈无政府局势的唯一药方
The plebiscite was the only and urgent remedy against anarchy. Believe me.
我们的罪恶是次要的
For us it's only a lesser evil.
毕竟，萨瓦…
The Savoyards, basically...
仍然是君主制
...are a monarchy.
我承认，你所爱人们的利益…
The interests of the people you love, to whom you are devoted...
的确被这些事情所破坏了…
...emerge from these events thwarted, I agree...
但他们还活着，还很健康
...but still alive, still valid.
万物要保持永恒
Something had to change...
就必须作出改变
...so that everything might remain as it was before.
革命已经结束，但愿今天的意大利能繁荣昌盛
The revolution's work is done. Let's hope new Italy can live and prosper.
我不同意
But I voted NO.
市政厅的混蛋压制了我的意见，肆意对我口诛笔伐
The town hall pigs swallowed my opinion and shat it out as they chose.
我说黑，他们却让我说白
I said "black" and they've made me say "white".
我曾经是个“忠臣”，现在却成了“无耻的波旁拥党”
I was a "loyal subject" and I've become a "foul Bourbon".
他们现在都是萨瓦人
Now, they're all Savoyards.
但对我来说，萨瓦人只是棵菜！
Savoyards! I eat them for breakfast!
听我说，你很了解这里的人
Tell me something. You see so many in the district.
你觉得卡洛吉罗怎么样？
What do you really think of Don Calogero?
我想我已经清楚表达了我的意见
I thought I'd shown my opinion clearly enough.
我有兴趣知道他和他家的真相
I'd be quite interested to know the truth about him and his family.
殿下，真相就是，他很有钱…
The truth, Excellency, is that Don Calogero is very rich...
也很有影响力
...and also very influential.
他是个吝啬鬼，却像魔鬼般机灵
Avaricious, and fiendishly intelligent, too.
你该看看他去年四五月的模样，他像蝙蝠一样来往穿梭
You should have seen him in April and May, swooping about like a bat.
坐马车，骑马，骑骡子，走路，风雨无阻
In a carriage, riding a mule, or on foot, rain or shine.
他经过的地方，便会结成秘密组织…
Wherever he went, secret groups were formed...
为将要来的人铺路
...preparing the way for those who were to come.
他是个灾难！
A scourge of God, Excellency.
这只是他事业的开始
We've only seen the start of Don Calogero's career.
再过几个月，他会成为都灵议会的议员
In a few months, he'll be a member of the parliament in Turin.
再过几年，当教会财产被拍卖时…
In a few years, when the church's property is auctioned off...
他不费分文…
...for a handful of coins...
就能占有马拉及冯达希罗的资产
...he'll pick up their land at Fondacello...
最后，他会成为全省最大的地主
...and become the biggest landowner in the province.
这就是卡洛吉罗
There, that's who Don Calogero is...
未来的主宰者
...an example of the new man.
这样有点可惜
It's a pity he has to be like that.
他家的其他人怎么样？
And the rest of the family? What are the others like?
这些年没人见过他妻子
Nobody has seen Calogero's wife for years.
也许只有我才见过
Except myself, perhaps.
只有做弥撒时她才会出门，都是在早上五点没人的时候
She comes out only to go to first Mass, at five, when no one's about.
我有次故意很早起床去看她
Once I got up early specially, just to see her.
她像太阳般一样美丽！
Word of honour, she's as beautiful as the sun.
你不能责怪卡洛吉罗…不让妻子与别人接触
You can't blame him, cockroach though he is, for keeping her from other men.
但天下没有不漏风的墙
But even from the best-guarded houses...
闲言碎语不时从仆人口中说出
...word trickles out, servants talk.
唐娜·帕斯蒂安娜像只动物
It seems that Donna Bastiana is a kind of animal.
她不会看书写字，也不知道时间，她只会说话
Illiterate, can't tell the time, she hardly knows how to speak.
她甚至不会喜欢女儿
She's incapable, too, of loving her daughter.
一无是处，除了在床上
Good for bed, and that's all.
不过，你知道她是谁的女儿吗？
Besides, it can't be otherwise. Do you know whose daughter she was?
她是伦奇一个农民的女儿
One of your share-croppers at Runci.
她父亲名叫派波·吉安塔
Peppe Giunta his name was.
他野蛮无耻，大家都叫他派波·牛粪
He was so foul-smelling and uncouth, everyone called him Peppe Shit.
请原谅我语言粗俗
Excuse the word, Excellency.
卡洛吉罗和帕斯蒂安娜私奔两年后…
Two years after Don Calogero ran off with Bastiana...
人们发现她父亲死了，背上中了十二枪
...Peppe was found dead with twelve shotgun pellets in his back.
我还指望他和康塞塔结婚呢！
And I hoped that Tancredi would marry Concetta.
他是叛党，那些自由党人都是！
He's a traitor, like all such liberals.
他先背叛国王，现在背叛我们
First he betrayed the king, and now us.
他有一副说谎者的嘴脸…
He with his false face...
甜言蜜语，道德败坏！
...with his words dripping honey and his actions dripping poison.
家里有个不同宗的亲戚…
This is what happens...
就会有这样的后果
...when you take into your house people not of your own blood.
我一直都这样说，但没人听我的！
I always said so, but nobody listens to me.
我受不了这种花花公子！他让你昏了头！
I never could stand that dandy. You alone were enamoured of him.
他居然还好意思请你这个舅舅…
And now he has the effrontery to ask you, his uncle, Prince of Salina...
请他欺骗的那个女孩的父亲，去向那个混蛋提亲…
...father of the girl he's deceived, to take his proposal to that rogue...
去向那个荡妇的父亲提亲！你不能这么做！
...the father of that trollop... Fabrizio, you shall not do it!
你知道自己在说什么吗！安杰莉卡不是荡妇
You don't know what you're saying. Angelica is not a trollop.
将来的事说不准，但现在她和其他女孩一样…
She may become one, but now she's like any other girl, only more beautiful...
比其他女孩更美丽，她只希望嫁个好男人
...who simply wants to make a good marriage.
她也可以和其他女孩一样，爱上塔克罗迪
Maybe she's a little in love with our Tancredi, as they all are, after all.
她有很多钱
And she has a lot of money, Stella.
卡洛吉罗管理着我们大部分的财产…
Our money, largely, administered well, too well even, by Don Calogero.
塔克罗迪需要这笔钱
Tancredi needs that money.
他是名绅士，他雄心勃勃
He's a nobleman, ambitious, spendthrift. He needs a lot of money.
他从未向康塞塔承诺过什么，所以不存在背叛
As for Concetta, he's never said anything to her, so he's no traitor.
他只是顺应时势…政治生涯和感情生活都是如此
He moves with his times, that's all. Both in politics and in private life.
而且，他是个招人喜欢的年轻人，这点你也知道
Besides, he's the dearest young man I know. Even you know that.
我不想在家里听到任何哭声！在我房里或是床上！
I want no whimpering in my house, either in my room or in my bed.
不要再说“你不能这样”，我决定了
No more "You shall not do it". I make the decisions.
我很早前就决定了，不要再提这件事
I decided this long ago. And now no more about it.
睡吧
Now let us sleep.
明天我去打猎，得早起
Tomorrow I am getting up early to go hunting.
你说了很多他们的事，野蛮的母亲，无耻的祖父
You've told me about them all: wild mothers and faecal grandfathers...
但我感兴趣的是…安杰莉卡小姐
...but nothing about what interests me, about Angelica.
没什么好说的，显而易见
There's nothing to say. She speaks for herself.
她继承了母亲的美貌，摒弃了祖父的恶习，是位真正的淑女
Her mother's beauty without her grandfather's stench. A real lady.
她从学校放假回来，曾邀请我去她家跳老式的玛祖卡舞
When she returned from college she played me the old mazurka I wrote.
看到她让人心情愉悦
She played badly, but to see her was a delight...
黑色的长发，漂亮的眼睛，光滑的皮肤，丰满的胸部
...with her black hair, those eyes, that skin, that bosom.
与那些凡尘女子有着天壤之别
Some difference from the stink of goats.
她的味道像天堂般美妙
Her sheets must have the fragrance of paradise.
冷静点
Calm down, Don Ciccio.
从现在起，不能对她有非份之想
From now on you'll have to speak of Angelica with all due respect.
今天，我会代表塔克罗迪去向卡洛吉罗提亲
This very day I'm asking Calogero for her hand for my nephew Tancredi.
你是第一个知道的，但要为这种特权付出代价
You're the first to know, but you'll pay for this privilege.
我会把你跟狗关在军械室里…
You'll be locked up in the gun-room with the dogs...
直到我见完卡洛吉罗，我不想走漏半点风声
...until after Calogero's visit. I want nothing to leak out in advance.
这样做太无耻了
This is disgraceful, obscene.
他不能娶你敌人的女儿为妻，那些人一直都反对你
He can't marry the daughter of your enemies. They've always opposed you.
引诱她也许是种征服，但娶她则是无条件投降
If he seduced her, that would be a conquest, but this is pure surrender.
这是法康利和萨利纳家族的终结
It's the end of the Falconeri family and the Salinas.
这并非一切的终结，而是开始
The marriage is not the end of anything, but the start.
婚姻是最好的解决办法
And it's in our best traditions.
有些事情你不明白
These are things you can't understand.
回家吧，你记得答应过我什么？
Let's go home. And we're agreed, aren't we?
别反客为主，区区一个吻何足大惊小怪！
Let there be no misunderstanding, or a big fuss over a little kiss.
别忘了，是我叫你来的
Remember, it was I who asked you to come here.
我想跟你说说我外甥的信
I wish to tell you about a letter written by my nephew...
昨晚收到的
...received this very night, in fact.
他在信中表达了对令爱的钦慕之情…
In it he declares his love for your daughter...
并请我郑重地…
...and asks me to ask you...
向您提亲
...officially, for Angelica's hand.
说说你的想法
Now it's your turn to declare your intentions.
请见谅，殿下
Excuse me, Prince.
我惊喜得都透不过气了
This lovely surprise has robbed me of speech.
我知道安杰莉卡心里的想法…
I know well what Angelica feels in her heart and mind...
塔克罗迪对小女的喜爱…
...and I think that Tancredi's feelings, which honour us all...
让我们受宠若惊
...are sincerely reciprocated.
愿上帝保佑这门亲事
We ask for God's protection for this wedding.
恭喜了，殿下
Your joy is mine, Excellency.
暴风雨要来了
It's turning stormy.
我不必告诉你法康利人多么杰出
No need for me to tell you how illustrious the Falconeri family is.
他们和查尔斯·安如一同来到西西里…
It came to Sicily with Charles of Anjou, flourished under the Aragons...
在阿拉贡，西班牙和波旁皇室时期发展旺盛…
...the Spanish kings and the Bourbons, if you'll allow me to mention them.
他们有世袭贵族，西班牙大公，圣地亚哥爵士…
They were peers of the realm, grandees of Spain, Knights of St. James.
我没必要告诉你法康利家族的历史…
But if there's no need to tell you of the history of the house of Falconeri...
我也没必要告诉你我外甥的实际情况…
...I need not tell you, alas, because you already know...
并不像他的名号那么优秀，这一点你也知道
...that my nephew's fortune does not match the grandeur of his name.
我姐夫不是有远见的家长
My brother-in-law was not what one calls a provident father.
他奢华的生活影响了我外甥
The sumptuousness of his life impaired my nephew's inheritance.
但卡洛吉罗，所有问题的结果…
But, Don Calogero, the result of all these troubles...
就是塔克罗迪
...of these heartbreaks, is Tancredi.
这些我们都明白
The two of us know these things.
也许，没人能像塔克罗迪…
Perhaps it is impossible to be as distinguished...
那么高贵，敏感，迷人…
...sensitive and charming as Tancredi...
除非他的祖先大肆挥霍，至少在西西里是如此
...unless ancestors have squandered fortunes. That's how it is in Sicily.
这些我都清楚…
I know all this, and more besides.
不过，殿下，爱情就是一切…
But love, Excellency, love is all...
我是这样认为的
...as I know well.
想想看…
Now listen
我是个通世故的人，我有话直说
I'm a man of the world and I'll put my cards on the table, too.
年轻人应该明白不能指望他们
These young people must know what they can count on.
在婚约中，我会将塞特索尼的财产所有权…
In the marriage contract, I'll assign to my daughter...
归到我女儿名下
...the deeds to Settesoli.
一千零一十公顷麦地
One thousand and ten hectares.
全都是一等地…
All wheat fields, first-class land...
凉爽通风
...cool and airy...
吉比多克五百公顷的葡萄园…
...and five hundred hectares of vineyards and olive groves...
还有橄榄园
...at Gibildolce.
结婚那天…
On the wedding day I'll give the bridegroom...
我会给新郎二十万盎司金币
...twenty bags, each with 10,000 uncias.
对我而言，家庭就是一切
My family means everything to me.
除了我，这些年没人见过他妻子
Nobody has seen Calogero's wife for years.
只有做弥撒时她才会出门
Except myself, perhaps. She comes out only to go to first Mass...
早上五点趁着教堂没人时
...at five, when no one's about.
我有次故意很早起床去看她
Once I got up early specially, just to see her.
她像太阳一样美丽！
Word of honour, she's as beautiful as the sun.
你不能责怪卡洛吉罗…
You can't blame him, cockroach though he is...
不让妻子与别人接触
...for keeping her from other men.
除了女儿之外，我只有少得可怜的财产
Of course, it leaves me a beggar, but a daughter is a daughter.
我知道我说的话…
And after all, Prince, I know what I'm telling you...
对你没什么影响，你是提图斯帝王…
...won't impress you, a descendant of Emperor Titus and Queen Berenice...
贝莱尼斯女王的后嗣，但瑟德拉家族…
...but the Sedara family, by a title granted by Ferdinand the Fourth...
也是贵族世家
...is also nobility.
文件我都还保存着，终有一天，你会知道你外甥…
I've all the papers in order. One day it will be known that your nephew...
娶的是瑟德拉女伯爵
...has married a baroness, the Baroness Sedara del Biscotto.
皮诺神父，文件我都整理好了，就差封条了
Don Pirrone, I've all the papers in order. Just one seal to get.
对不起，希斯奥，我也没办法
I'm sorry, Don Ciccio, but I had no choice.
我能理解，一切都顺利吗？
I hope at least that all went well.
很顺利，无比顺利
Yes, perfectly. It couldn't have gone better.
我们会很快见面的，请原谅我
We'll meet again soon. And forgive me.
“一月中旬寒冷的一天”
It was a cold January day.
“冷冽的北风将空气冻结…”
The atmosphere seemed even heavier when the biting north wind dropped.
“雪已纷纷扬扬下了几个小时…”
For many hours it had been snowing great white flakes.
“在人迹罕至的道路上，一匹可怜的马背上披着张粗糙的毯子…”
On that deserted road, a poor old horse, a rough blanket on its back...
正吃力地拉着一辆马车
...wearily dragged a two-wheeled cart.
“驾！该死的”！农民口中喊着…
"Oh, you damned beast", cried the peasant...
“他平时就是这样和马说话的”
...who habitually talked to his horse.
殿下，塔克罗迪少爷来了！
Excellency, Don Tancredi has arrived.
他在花园里卸行李
He is in the courtyard having his luggage unloaded.
别走太近，舅舅，我全身都湿透了
Not too close, uncle. I'm as wet as a sponge.
很高兴再见到你
How pleased I am to see you again.
塔克罗迪，安杰莉卡一定很高兴的
Tancredi, think how happy Angelica will be.
对不起，我兴奋得都忘了
Forgive me, but my emotion caused me to forget.
这位是加里亚吉伯爵，他曾和将军一起去过别墅
My friend, Count Cavriaghi. He came to the villa with the General.
那位是我的勤务兵，兰西·莫洛尼
And there is my orderly, Lancer Moroni.
我们一直盼着你来，不过天气…
We were expecting you, but in this weather...
大雨天他们都赶回来了
They arrived in this storm.
听说这里从不下雨
I'd heard it never rains here.
前两天都是倾盆大雨
For two days it was like being in the sea. Really.
舅妈，这位是从米兰来的加里亚吉伯爵，你在巴勒莫见过他的
Aunt, here's Count Cavriaghi from Milan. You met him in Palermo.
你说这里从不下雨，你看，不下则已，一下倾盆！
You thought it never rains in Sicily. As you've seen, it pours.
别以为这里没有肺炎，当心会患上感冒哦
And don't think there's no pneumonia here, or you'll end up in bed.
把塔克罗迪和客房的火生起来
Light fires in Tancredi's room and in the visitor's room.
把隔壁房间收拾一下，给勤务兵
Get the next room ready for the soldier. Hurry!
我真不明白你们这些人
I don't understand, boys.
上次你们不是穿红军装的吗？
Last time you were lobster-red.
什么意思？
What do you mean?
加里波第的军队不穿红军装了吗？
Don't you Garibaldi fellows wear the red shirt any more?
那些人都成为过去了！
Garibaldi fellows be blowed!
我们曾经是，但现在都结束了
We were, but now that's over.
加里亚吉和我，感谢上帝…
Cavriaghi and I, thank heaven...
我们是意大利皇家军队的军官
...are officers of the regular army of His Majesty the King of Italy.
加里波第的部队解散后，我们有两个选择…
When Garibaldi's army was disbanded we had the choice:
要么回家，要么加入皇家军
either return home, or stay in the royal army.
我们俩，还有很多人，加入了真正的军队
We and many others decided to join the proper army.
我们不能再呆在暴民军队里了，对吧，加里亚吉
We couldn't stay with that lot, could we, Cavriaghi?
太可怕了
What rabble!
他们只会埋伏抢劫
Assault troops, good for firing guns, that's all.
我们现在是真正的军官
Now we're proper officers.
人们不用再担心我们会偷鸡！
People no longer fear we'll steal their chickens.
我们从巴勒莫来这里时…
When we came here from Palermo...
只要说一句“国王的命令”便会有人送给我们马匹
...we had only to say: "Urgent orders for His Majesty" to get fresh horses.
迟点再跟我们说，现在去换衣服吧
Tell me everything later. Now go and change and have a bath.
先给你们看看送给安杰莉卡的戒指
First I want to show you the ring for Angelica.
我不是行家，不过看起来很值钱
I'm no judge, but it looks valuable.
是不是很漂亮？喜欢吗？
Beautiful, isn't it? Do you like it?
价格不菲吧？
Did you pay a lot for it?
我把钱都用在刀刃上了，你给我的钱没用光的
I used your money well. I confess I haven't used all you gave me.
☆剩下的钱还够买不少东西★见面礼是吗？
☆There was even enough to buy...★Some parting gifts? I understand.
中尉回来了，那是什么？
Our lieutenant is back. What is that?
给康塞塔小姐的礼物
A small present for signorina Concetta.
《亚罗迪诗集》，希望她会喜欢
"The Poems of Aleardi". I hope she likes it.
亚罗迪诗集，我最喜欢他的诗
They are poems by Aleardi, my favourite poet.
小小礼物，请笑纳
I brought it as a gift. I've had your monogram inscribed here.
“永远的聋小姐”，什么聋小姐？我听觉正常
"Always deaf"? What does it mean? I hear perfectly.
但听不到我的叹息
Deaf to my sighs.
对不起，我听说…
Excuse me, but I was told...
这是我送你的礼物
A gift for you from your Tancredi.
你得谢谢舅舅
You can thank my uncle, too.
安杰莉卡，塔克罗迪，你们在哪？
Angelica! Tancredi! Where are you?
这里到处都有老鼠
It's mouse-ridden.
来啊
Come along.
安杰莉卡，你在哪？
Angelica, where are you?
塔克罗迪，你在哪？
Tancredi, where are you?
你吓到我了，到处都有老鼠
How frightening. Do you know there are mice here?
没有老鼠才怪，塔克罗迪呢？
I'm sure, in this house. But where is Tancredi?
我找不到他
I can't find him.
塔克罗迪，安杰莉卡，你们在哪儿？
Tancredi! Angelica! Where are you?
吓坏你了吧？
I frightened you, didn't I?
又是她，我们快走
There she is again. Let's run away.
不，我们去哪儿？我累死了
No. Where are we going? I'm dead tired.
宫殿到底有多大？有多少间房？
How big the place is. How many rooms are there?
没人知道，连舅舅都不知道
No one knows, not even my uncle.
他说，住在一座自己熟悉的宫殿，是很没意思的
He says a palace where you know all the rooms isn't worth living in.
☆我们去找她吧，可怜的女孩★其他人呢？
☆Come on, the poor thing is alone.★What about the others?
康塞塔回花园了
Concetta has gone back to the garden.
你舅舅让弗兰西斯科…
Francesco Paolo was sent by your uncle...
去迎接一位客人了
...to welcome a guest.
☆是谁？★不知道，从都灵来的
☆Who is he?★I don't know. He's from Turin.
走吧
Then let's go.
不，我不去了
No, I don't want to see anything else
我要走了，我在这里干嘛？康塞塔根本不爱我
I'm leaving. What am I doing here? Concetta doesn't love me.
你向她表白了吗？
Have you spoken to her?
没用的，在她面前…
It's useless. I feel that for her...
我就是一条虫，我要去找一条与我匹配的母虫
...I'm just a worm. So I must find a lady worm who'll be happy with me.
向她表白吧，迟点下定论也不晚，没准一切都会好的
Talk to her. There'll be time later to decide. Maybe it's all for the best.
康塞塔是地道的西西里人，从没离开过这里
I'll explain: Concetta's a pure Sicilian, she's never left the island.
在米兰，她会觉得不自在，米兰人吃面要提前一个月准备
How would she cope in Milan, where it takes a month to find real macaroni?
我可以为她准备比这长凳还大的一箱面条
I'd have got her crates of your macaroni, bigger than this.
我们走了
We'll make our way separately, then?
可怜的伯爵，康塞塔不会看上她的
Poor Count, it's useless. Concetta does not want to know him.
傻瓜，她还奢求什么？
She's foolish. After all, what does she want?
加里亚吉相貌英俊，荣誉和财富兼备
Cavriaghi is handsome, has a good name, owns land in Brianza.
这就是典型的如意郎君
He's what's known as a good catch.
康塞塔还爱着你
Concetta is still in love with you.
这就是你带伯爵来的原因
That's why you brought him here.
肯定是
Yes, that's what I think.
我说了不是
No, I'll tell you.
听我说，康塞塔没错
Then listen carefully. Concetta's right.
嫁给他就好比喝白开水，而之前喝的是…
Marrying someone like him after loving you would be like water after...
☆是什么？★葡萄酒
☆After what?★Let's say Marsala wine.
好奇怪的房子，这种地方怎么可以住人？
Strange rooms. How could anyone have lived in such apartments?
实际上，没人住过这里
No one has ever lived here, my love.
前人来这里打破习俗…
My ancestors came here to commit their little breaches of the rules...
留下与众不同的甜蜜回忆
...and obtain special memories so different from ordinary mortals.
打破习俗？
Breaches of the rules?
讨厌的习俗，亲爱的
They were bored, my love.
阁下是希弗利先生吗？
Are you the Chevalier Aymone Chevalley de Monterzuolo?
正是
I am.
我是萨利纳王子的儿子
I am the Prince of Salina's son.
家父邀请您去宫殿小住
My father sent me to invite you to stay with us at the palace.
十分感谢
That's very kind of you.
您把帽子戴上吧，太阳很晒
Do replace your hat. Our sun is strong.
谢谢，你也戴上吧
Thank you. You, too.
我打算跟殿下见面后就动身
I did intend to leave as soon as I had talked with the Prince.
和我父亲谈的话得先去我家
In any case, to talk to my father you'll have to come home.
是那座宫殿吗？
Is that the palace up there?
塔克罗迪和安杰莉卡呢？
Where are Tancredi and Angelica?
他们不在楼上，肯定在花园里
Not upstairs. They must have returned to the garden.
太糟糕了，我得陪着安杰莉卡的
It's terrible. You know I must chaperone Angelica.
你怕我不再爱你吗？
Do you think I won't love you any more?
不用担心
You're afraid.
我想拥有你，但我要等到你成为我妻子
I desire you, but I won't possess you until you are my wife.
我的腿累坏了
My poor leg, I'm afraid.
客人到了
Here's the guest.
他想你怎么帮他？
What does he want from you?
我不知道，他来西西里一个月了，一定很可怜
I don't know. He's travelled round Sicily for a month. He must be forlorn.
一定是这里的饭菜他吃不惯
The oil in our cooking must have sorely tried his insides.
虽然内心不安，但他仍怕别人看出来
He fears a brigand's knife in the stomach, which he still cherishes.
我想跟他打牌
I'd like to suggest we play whist.
玩牌怎么样？
What do you say to a game of cards?
殿下，我想单独跟您谈谈，我明天就得走了
Excellency, if I could have the honour of a talk. I must leave tomorrow.
明天？在这里住得不习惯吗？
Leave tomorrow? Are you not comfortable here?
当然不是
Yes, certainly.
亲爱的希弗利，你现在在我家…
My dear Chevalley, you are in my house...
我想扣留你多久就多久
...and I'll hold you hostage as long as I please.
你得小心皮诺神父，他总是赢
Beware of Father Pirrone, he's a terror. He always wins.
请坐，我和你一组
Please be seated. I'll be your partner.
我来记分
I'll keep the score.
你真是米兰人？怎么会来这里的？
Excuse me, are you really from Milan? However did you end up down here?
我在殿下家里感觉很自在
Although I abuse the Prince's hospitality, I feel much at home here.
我可以做你在杜纳福卡特的导游，带你去莫托洛男爵家参观
Let me be your guide in Donnafugata. I'll show you Baron Mutolo's house.
弗兰西斯科，别这样说话
Francesco Paulo, don't start that.
那里没人了，自从十年前男爵的儿子被绑架…
It's empty. The family lives at Girgenti...
他们家就一直住在这里
...since brigands held the Baron's son for ransom ten years ago.
真可怜，他们花了多少钱赎回孩子？
When I think what they must have paid to free him.
没花，他们当时和其他人一样很拮据
They paid nothing. They had no ready cash, like everybody here.
不过，那孩子最终还是回来了…分段回来
The son was returned, anyway, but in installments
分段？什么意思？
In installments? What are you saying?
分段，一点点回来的
Yes, installments: piece by piece.
先是右手的食指
First came the index finger of his right hand.
一个星期后，是左脚
Then, a week later, his left foot.
最后，一个篮子里放着无花果…
Finally, in a basket under a layer of figs...
下面是他的头
...they sent his head.
弗兰西斯科，别说了！
That's enough of those stories.
当时我还小，没亲眼看到，是父亲告诉我的
I never saw it because I was a child, but my father told me.
波旁皇族的警察太没用了
I'd say the Bourbon police were incompetent.
没错
Without doubt, Chevalley.
我们村里也发生过悲惨的事故，我父亲是位工头…
We had incidents in our region. My father was an overseer...
直到不久前，对于家庭来说…
...a risky job, at least until a while ago...
工头是份危险的职业
...for him and for his family.
卡宾枪手会让这一切不再发生
When our carabinieri come here, all this will end.
跟宣传内容相反的是…
So, contrary to certain propaganda...
人们会像从前一样尊敬和捍卫教堂
...respect for the church will be restored and defended as it once was.
但愿能胜过以前
Let us hope a little better...
五年前，一位牧区牧师在做弥撒时被杀
...because five years ago a curate was murdered while he conducted Mass.
天哪！他在教堂被开枪打死的？
How horrible. A shooting in the church?
开枪？怎么会
Shooting, my dear Chevalley?
我们是虔诚的天主教徒，不会这样做
We're too good Catholics to do anything so sacrilegious.
凶手只是在牧师的酒中下毒
No, they simply put poison in the communion wine.
凶手很谨慎，以宗教作幌子
More discreet, almost liturgical, I'd say.
查不出凶手是谁，牧师是个好人，从不与人树敌
But who did it? The curate was an excellent person who had no enemies.
很有意思，真好听
Very interesting, Prince, really amusing.
你应该写小说，你故事说得很好
You should write novels. You tell these stories so well.
没错，是在说故事，我毕竟是从米兰来的
Yes, they're all stories. Believe me, I'm from Milan.
西西里人杰地灵
Sicily is a great country.
幸福的结合之后…
After the happy annexation...
西西里和撒丁王国合并之后…
...that is, after the happy union of Sicily and the Kingdom of Sardinia...
都灵政府打算推荐一些
...it's the intention of the Turin government...
杰出的西西里人担任参议员
...to nominate certain illustrious Sicilians as Senators of the Kingdom.
阁下也在推荐之列
Of course, your name was among the first.
因为历史悠久的家族…
A name made illustrious by its long history...
阁下的声望与博学…
...by the prestige of its bearer...
在最近的事件中表现出的高贵与慷慨…
...his erudition and the dignified and liberal action taken in recent events.
我的上司觉得在名单递交到都灵之前…
Before I send the list to Turin...
应该先知会您一声…
...my superiors thought it proper to inform you yourself...
看看您是否赞成这项提议
...and ask if you find the proposal acceptable.
政府希望得到您的同意
The government hopes very much that you will agree.
也就是这个任务…
This is the object of my mission...
让我有幸见到您和这座宏伟的宫殿
...which has given me the honour of knowing you and this fine palace.
希弗利，告诉我…
Explain to me, Chevalley...
当参议员是什么意思？
...what does it mean to be a Senator?
是怎么一回事？是荣誉头衔？是装饰？
What is it? An honorary title, like a decoration?
参议院是我国最高议院
The Senate is the Upper House of our kingdom.
参议院对政府提出的法律议案…
In it they examine and debate...
进行检查，讨论，通过或反对
...approve or reject laws proposed by government for the country's progress.
当上参议员后…
When you are a Senator...
要帮助政府倾听人民的心声
...you'll make heard the voice of your beautiful land...
我们即将进入现代社会…
...which now faces the panorama of the modern world...
政府要医治人们的创伤，满足他们的要求
...with so many wounds to heal, so many just desires to satisfy.
听着…
Listen, Chevalley.
我很感谢政府对我的器重
I'm grateful to the government for thinking of me for the Senate.
如果参议员仅仅只是名片上的一个头衔…
If it were a simple honorary title to put on my visiting card...
我会很乐意接受
...I'd accept with pleasure.
但它并非如此，所以我不能接受
But as it is... no, I cannot accept.
我是旧统治阶级的一员…
I am a spokesman of the old class...
无奈与旧政权联系在一起…
...fatally compromised with the past regime...
那是形式上的联系，而不是感情上的
...bound to it by bonds of decency, if not affection.
我跨越两个世界，在两个世界中都觉得不安
My unhappy generation straddles two worlds and is uneasy in either.
而且，我不抱有任何幻想
Moreover, I am completely without illusions.
参议院怎能接纳一位毫无经验的成员…
What would the Senate do with me, an inexperienced legislator...
一位不能自欺欺人…没能力指导他人的成员？
...who lacks self-deception, which is essential when seeking to guide others?
不，我不能插手政治，那样便不能全身而退
No, I wouldn't put one finger into politics. They'd bite it off.
难以置信
Prince, I can't believe it.
你真的不愿意尽你所能来减轻我国人民…
Are you seriously refusing to do whatever possible to alleviate...
所承受的物质贫穷和精神痛苦吗？
...the material poverty and blind moral misery in which Sicilians lie?
我们老了，希弗利，老了
We are old, Chevalley, very old.
二十五个世纪以来，我们所肩负的伟大文明皆来自外部…
For twenty-five centuries we have borne magnificent civilizations...
而非由我们创造，不能称为我们的文明
...all from abroad, none made by us, none which started here.
两千五百年来，除了殖民者，我们什么都不是
For 2,500 years we've been nothing but a colony.
我并非抱怨，是我们的错
I don't say that to scourge myself. It's our fault.
但我们已累得精疲力尽
But we are very tired, empty, burnt-out.
可是现在都结束了
But all that is finished now.
西西里不再是殖民地，而是自由国家的一名自由成员
Sicily is no longer a land of conquest, but a free part of a free state.
你的好意我心领了，不过太迟了
The intention is good, but it arrives late.
亲爱的希弗利，西西里人的愿望就是沉睡在梦里
A sleep, my dear Chevalley. A long sleep is what the Sicilians want...
他们憎恨将他们叫醒的人…
...and they'll always hate those who want to wake them...
即使他们带来丰厚的礼物
...even if it is to bring them marvellous gifts.
说句实话，我不知道新王国会给我们带来什么礼物
Between ourselves, I doubt if the new kingdom will have many gifts for us.
所有的呐喊，甚至最暴力的，都是渴望遗忘
With us, every demonstration, even violent, is a longing for oblivion.
寻欢作乐是为了遗忘
Our sensuality is a desire for oblivion.
枪林弹雨是渴望死亡
Our shootings and our stabbings are the desire for death.
懒惰，甘甜的饮料…
Our laziness, the penetrating sweetness of our sorbets...
都是为了奢华的安宁…也就是死亡
...are a desire for voluptuous immobility, which again is death.
殿下，您太夸张了吧？
Prince, aren't you exaggerating?
我在都灵遇到的西西里人根本没有沉睡
I've met Sicilians in Turin. They seemed anything but sluggards.
我表达得不好，对不起
I haven't explained very well. I'm sorry.
我刚刚说西西里人，应该是西西里
I said Sicilians, I meant Sicily.
危险的环境，暴力肆虐的地方…
This environment, the violence of the landscape...
恶劣的气候，一切都充满着紧张和不安…
...the cruelty of the climate, the continuous tension in everything.
气候可以改善，环境可以改善
But the climate can be mastered, the landscape can be modified...
罪恶的统治也能推翻
...the record of bad governments erased.
西西里人当然渴望改善
Of course, the Sicilians will want to improve.
我不否认，有些人一旦离开西西里就会觉醒…
I don't deny that some, away from the island, can succeed in awakening.
但必须很小时就离开，二十岁的话个性已经成形了
But they must leave very young. Even at twenty the shell has been formed.
你需要的是一位…
The man you need...
能把个人利益和公众理想合而为一的贤能
...must know how to temper his private interests with vague public idealism.
我可以向你上司提点建议吗？
Might I give you some advice to pass on to your superiors?
我想推荐一个人当参议员
There's a name I'd like to suggest for the Senate.
卡洛吉罗·瑟德拉
The name of Calogero Sedara.
他比我更适合当议员
He deserves much more than I to be elected.
他的家族历史悠久
The family name, I'm told, is very ancient★or will be soon.
他具备你所谓的威望，他有权力
He has more than what you call prestige. He has power.
他具备的优点很实用，可谓是才华横溢
He may not be learned, but he has almost exceptional practical merits.
五月危机中他贡献突出
His activity was most useful during the May crisis...
至于幻想…
...as far as illusions go.
他和我一样没有幻想…
I don't think he has more than I have...
但他能在所需之时创造幻想，他是最佳人选
...but he's clever enough to create some himself. He's the man for you.
我也听说过瑟德拉
I've heard tell about Sedara.
但阁下这样的正直之士都退缩…
But if honest men like you withdraw...
等于将机会拱手给毫无远见的鲁莽匹夫…
...the road will be open to people without scruples or perspective...
就像瑟德拉之类…以后一切又会和以前一样
...like Sedara, and for centuries to come all will be as it was.
想想你的良心…而不是你说的这些丰功伟绩
Listen to your conscience, Prince, not to the proud truths you spoke.
求你了，与我们合作
I beg you to collaborate.
你是位绅士，希弗利，认识你的确是种荣幸
You're a gentleman and I consider it a privilege to have known you.
你说的都有道理…
You are right in everything.
除了一句话，“西西里人当然渴望改善”
Except when you say the Sicilians will want to improve.
他们从未渴望改善，他们觉得自己最完美
They'll never want to improve because they think themselves perfect.
虚荣比贫困更甚
Their vanity is stronger than their wretchedness.
请坐
Sit down for a moment.
我给你讲个故事
I want to tell you something.
加里波第进入巴勒莫之前…
A few days before Garibaldi entered Palermo...
英国战舰的军官请我允许…
...some English naval officers...
他们上去我家的房顶…
...asked me if they could go on the terrace of my house...
在那可以看到周围环绕的山丘
...where they could see the ring of mountains around the city.
风景让他们陶醉…
They were enthusiastic about the view...
但他们坦言说贫穷肮脏的街道让人触目惊心
...but confessed their amazement at the squalor and filth in the streets.
我并没有像对你这样…
I didn't explain, as I did with you, that the one derived from the other.
一位军官问…
One of the officers asked:
“加里波第要来西西里干什么？”
"What are Garibaldi's men coming to do here?"
我回答说，“他来教我们礼仪…”
I replied: "They're coming to teach us manners."
“但他不会成功，因为我们就是上帝”
"But they won't succeed, because we're gods."
他们哈哈大笑，但他们并不明白
They laughed, but I don't think they understood.
很晚了，是时间吃饭了
It's late, almost time for dinner.
我们得去换衣服
We must go and change.
你可以明天一早就走
If you wish, you can leave tomorrow at dawn.
也许你不相信，这种状态不会持久
Even if you don't believe me, this state of affairs won't last.
政府有效的现代管理会将一切改变
Our efficient, modern administration will change everything.
这一切不该持久，但还会一直继续
This state of affairs ought not to last, but it always will.
“一直”，就是一两百年
The human element, certainly. A century or two.
一两百年后也许会变…不过是变得更糟糕
Later, perhaps everything will be different, but it will be worse.
我们是豹子，是狮子
We were the leopards, the lions.
取代我们的是豺狼，土狼
Those who replace us will be the jackals, the hyenas.
所有人，豹子，狮子，豺狼，土狼…
And all of us, leopards, lions, jackals and sheep...
我们都觉得自己很高尚
...will continue to think we're the salt of the earth.
我没听清，您说什么？
I don't quite understand. What did you say?
没什么
Nothing.
什么？我听不清
What did you say? I didn't hear.
你们来早了，没关系，客人还没到
You've arrived early. Don't worry, there's no sign of your guests yet.
塔克罗迪也来了，我们在等阿斯普洛蒙特的英雄巴勒维西诺
Tancredi's here. We're expecting Pallavicino, the hero of Aspromonte.
谢谢你，舅妈，请他们是很有必要的
Thank you again, aunt. It was essential to invite them.
这是安杰莉卡首次参加社交活动
You understand. This will be Angelica's real debut in society.
卡洛吉罗穿什么燕尾服？
What about Calogero's tail-suit?
不是他在杜纳福卡特穿的那套
It's not the one he wore at Donnafugata.
我请了最好的裁缝，衣服好看，只是他衬不起来
I took him to the best tailor. It's Don Calogero who lacks style.
☆-我可以去跳舞吗，妈妈？★当然可以，宝贝
☆Mamma, may I go and dance?★Of course. Tidy yourself a little.
你像花一样美丽！
You are very beautiful, like a flower.
我不喜欢这些舞会，但为了女儿不得不来
I don't care for these balls, but one had to come for the girls.
上校！很荣幸能见到您
Colonel, I am most honoured to see you.
玛格丽特，过来，这位是巴勒维西诺上校
I have the honour to present you to Colonel Pallavicino.
阿斯普洛蒙特的英雄光临塞舍，实在荣幸之至
I am proud and happy to receive the victor of Aspromonte in my house.
您太客气了，谢谢您邀请我来
How kind, Princess. It is I who am happy on this occasion.
祝你们玩得开心
I hope you and your officers will spend a pleasant evening in our home.
太荣幸了，上校，整个帕勒莫都在你脚下了
It really is an honour for us. All Palermo is at your feet, Colonel.
蓝佩杜萨王妃
The Princess of Lampedusa.
苏特拉伯爵夫人
Countess Sutera.
萨利纳的王妃
The Princess of Salina.
我去看看安杰莉卡到了没有
I'm going to see if Angelica has arrived.
上校，跟我们说说，这是真的吗？
Colonel, but tell us, is it really true?
我当时哭得像个小孩
I was crying, Countess, like a child.
太感人了
How moving.
加里波第长得怎么样？
But what was Garibaldi like?
他像大天使一样英俊平和
He was handsome and serene as an archangel.
他不愧是个真正的英雄，你说呢，亲爱的？
Magnificent, a hero. A real hero. Isn't he extraordinary, my dear?
在下令向加里波第的人开枪前，上校在试着让人们宽心
The Colonel is trying to reassure them after his men fired on Garibaldi's men.
开枪要恰到好处
Those shots were really most opportune.
你迟到了，我在等你
You're late. I was waiting for you.
你好美，过来见过王妃
You are very beautiful. Come and greet the Princess.
这位是我的未婚妻，安杰莉卡
Permit me to present my fiance, Angelica Sedara.
让我看看你，宝贝
My dear, let me look at you.
你比别人说的更漂亮
Yes, it's true. You are more beautiful than they say.
☆这是什么？★意大利王冠十字勋章
☆What's this?★Knight's Cross of the Italian Crown.
不过，这里用不着
It's out of place here.
我从不怀疑你的眼光
I've never doubted your good taste.
这是我的准岳父，卡洛吉罗
My father-in-law, the Chevalier Don Calogero Sedara.
☆这里很美★你喜欢吗？
☆Nice here, isn't it, Princess?★You like it?
塔克罗迪，你不介绍未婚妻给我认识吗？
Tancredi, don't you want to present me to your fiance?
安杰莉卡，这是我的朋友，吉奥奇罗
Allow me to present a friend, Gioacchino Lanza.
这位是弗科
And this is Fulco...
如果塔克罗迪不介意，可以请你跳支华尔兹吗？
Tancredi may protest, but may I have the honour of the next waltz?
别着急，伙计，时间多的是
All right, boys. Don't hurry, there'll be time later.
对不起，也不能怪我，请女士挑选舞伴
I'm sorry, I'm not to blame. The lady has to choose her partners.
华尔兹，跳舞好吗？
It's a waltz. Shall we dance?
☆我该和舅舅打个招呼★迟点也无妨
☆I haven't greeted your uncle yet.★Do it later. Come and dance.
你永远都这么美
You are very beautiful, as always. It's the truth.
很无聊吗，法里兹奥？
Bored, Fabrizio?
频繁的近亲结婚并没有改善血统
All these marriages between cousins do not improve the beauty of the race.
看看她们，活像一群猴子…
They look like monkeys, ready to climb up the chandeliers...
准备爬上烛台摇尾巴，露出屁股
...where they'll swing by their tails, exhibiting their behinds.
艾莉娜拉·加德娜丽…
Eleonora Giardinelli...
鹤立鸡群
...a white swan in a pond full of frogs.
对了，恭喜你外甥订婚
My compliments on your nephew's engagement.
那女孩很美，他们会成为典范的
The girl's a beauty. Many will soon follow his example.
你说什么？
What did you say?
这里太热了
I said it's hot, too hot here.
是很热，我不该来的
Yes, it is hot. I should not have come.
不过，既来之，则安之
I'm somewhat tired, but now I'm here and I must stay.
这样离场不大好
It would be discourteous to leave now.
晚上好，蒂娜，我都和吉奥瓦尼跳了四支舞了
Good evening. Tina, I have four dances booked with Giovanni.
王妃，能请您跳支舞吗？
Princess, I'd be most happy if you would do me the honour...
上校，我多年没跳舞了，这儿有这么多漂亮女士…
Colonel, it's years since I danced... so many lovely ladies are here...
这里真是个好地方
Nice, Prince, really beautiful.
如今没有这种房子了，金叶子价钱太高
Places like this aren't made nowadays, with the current price of gold.
是的，卡洛吉罗，是很漂亮
Yes, very nice, truly beautiful.
但没什么能和这对新人媲美
But nothing equals our two young people.
安杰莉卡来跟您打招呼，你怎么独自在这里？
Angelica wanted to greet you. But why are you here alone?
你在看什么？在感慨死亡？
Are you flirting with death?
你真美
You're really magnificent.
沉思中的帝亚哥看起来十分忧郁
Isn't it odd that Don Diego keeps this morbid picture?
他每年来一次的话就是奇迹了
If Don Diego enters this library once a year, it's a miracle.
你说得对
Yes, you're right.
不知道我死的时候是否也这样
I wonder if my death will resemble this.
亚麻布差了一点
The linen will not be so spotless.
临终时的床单总是很脏
The sheets of the dying are always so soiled...
希望我的女儿会穿得更高雅
...and I hope that Concetta and the others will be more decently dressed.
不过，我觉得都差不多
But I think all in all it will be the same.
舅舅，你在说什么？你在想什么？
What are you saying, uncle? What are you thinking of?
我经常想到死亡，但不畏惧死亡
I often think of death. The idea doesn't frighten me.
你们年轻人不明白
You young people cannot understand such things.
对你们来说，死亡遥不可及，好像只会发生在别人身上
For you, death does not exist, it's something for other people.
我们要把祖坟修葺一番
We must have repairs done to our family vault.
可以借你的手帕一用吗？
Give me your handkerchief, please.
殿下，听说您在这里，我们过来透气…
We knew you were here and we came for a rest...
也顺便问您一些事情
...but also to ask you something.
希望您不要推辞
I hope you won't refuse me.
我想请您和我跳下一支玛祖卡
I wanted to ask you to dance the next mazurka with me.
千万别拒绝我，谁都知道你舞跳得很好
Don't be lazy. Everyone knows you're a good dancer.
我从未听过比这更吸引的请求…
I've never had such an attractive proposal, but I must refuse.
求您了
Please, Prince.
你让我觉得自己又年轻了，不过别跳玛祖卡
You make me feel young again. I accept, but not the mazurka.
这样会让我觉得年轻过头的，跳华尔兹吧
That would make me feel too young. Grant me the next waltz.
你看舅舅多好，他不像你这么没风度
See how good your uncle is. He doesn't have tantrums like you.
他不想我请您跳舞，他吃醋了
He didn't want me to ask you. He's jealous.
这也很正常，谁让舅舅那么英俊潇洒？
When one has a handsome uncle like him, it's natural to be jealous.
不过，仅此一次，下不为例
But this time I'll make an exception.
华尔兹！看来乐队真是知我心意，你说呢？
A waltz, without even having to ask the orchestra. Do you like it?
华尔兹，您不是反悔了吧？
It's a waltz. Or perhaps you have already changed your mind.
不，当然不是
No, of course not.
大家都对我很好，我太开心了，舅舅
They're all so kind and I'm so happy, uncle.
塔克罗迪是个天使，您也是
Tancredi is a darling, and so are you.
还好塔克罗迪听不见
It's as well Tancredi can't hear you.
这一切都是您给我的
I know I owe everything to you.
包括塔克罗迪，要不是您同意…
So does Tancredi. Because if you had not wanted...
他也一样会和你结婚
He'd have married you, anyway.
这都是你争取来的
You owe everything to yourself.
不是这样的
No, it's not true.
是这样的，安杰莉卡
It is true, Angelica.
塔克罗迪绝对抵抗不了你的美貌
No man like Tancredi would ever have resisted your beauty.
别人告诉我你舞跳得好
I'd heard that you were a good dancer, Prince.
对不起，又让你失望了
I'm sorry to have disappointed you again.
你跳得简直好极了，和你共舞是件乐事
You're much more than a good dancer, you're a really delightful dancer.
是我父亲
Yes, it's my father.
☆下一支舞★玛祖卡
☆The next dance.★A mazurka, then.
大家都在看我们
They're all looking at us, Prince.
跟你父亲跳舞的女孩真漂亮
What a beautiful girl that is, dancing with your father.
没人鼓掌，肯定是因为大家尊重您
The applause was muted, because a lion commands respect...
不过您的确值得大家喝彩
...but you deserved an ovation.
过来跟我们一起吃饭吧
And now come to our table.
不，我青春的回忆还历历在目…
No, my memories of my youth are still vivid and I know very well...
我知道和舅舅共餐是多么无聊
...how boring it would be for you to dine with an old uncle.
不是这样的
That's not true.
恋人应该享受二人世界，况且，我也不饿
It is. Lovers wish to be alone. Anyway, I am not very hungry.
去和塔克罗迪吃吧，不用管我
Go with Tancredi and don't think of me.
法里兹奥，你的舞跳得还是那么好
Fabrizio, you're still a good dancer.
你好啊，法里兹奥
Fabrizio, how are you?
法里兹奥，您不吃吗？饭菜不合胃口？
Fabrizio, aren't you eating? You seem a little uncertain.
太多选择了，玛格丽特准备得很好
The choice is too great. Donna Margherita knows how to do things.
但我的胃吃不了这么多
All this calls for stomachs other than mine.
好漂亮的烛台！
How marvellous these candelabra are.
穆德里的东西，是帝亚哥父亲任大使时获赠的礼物
From Madrid. A gift to Don Diego's grandfather when he was ambassador.
真不知道这些值多少亩地
How much land would they be worth, eh?
我一生中最感动的时刻
The utmost emotion of my life.
真无聊！
What a great bore.
萨利纳殿下，能赏脸和我们一起吃吗？
Prince Salina. Will you do us the honour of sitting at our table?
左翼分子想把我钉死在十字架上…
Now the left wants to crucify me, because...
因为我在八月时下令向加里波第开火
...in August I ordered my lads to open fire on Garibaldi.
告诉我，殿下，我还能怎样呢？
But, Prince, what else could I do, with the written orders I had?
不过，说句实话…
I must confess, though...
当我在阿斯普洛蒙特面对那几百名叛党时…
...when at Aspromonte I faced those hundreds of Garibaldi's men...
有些是狂热者…
...some hardened veterans...
有些是鼓动者…
...others who looked like professional rebels...
所幸的是，我的行动与感情一致
I was happy those orders were so close to my own sentiments.
在这里悄悄告诉你吧…
Then, I'll tell you in confidence...
我开的那几枪还算帮了加里波第一把呢
...my short burst of shooting helped Garibaldi above all.
我把他从身边的乌合之众当中解救出来
I liberated him from the gang that had attached itself to him...
那些人各怀鬼胎利用加里波第
...who were using him for ends desired perhaps by Paris or Rome.
没错
Yes, it's true.
他们不像两年前在马沙登陆的那些人…
Individuals very different from those who landed at Marsala two years ago.
那些人相信，一八四八年的革命可让意大利获得新生
People who thought Italy could be created with revolutions like in 1848.
至于加里波第将军…
He... I mean General Garibaldi, as you know...
当我这般显赫的人向他鞠躬时，他握住我的手
...at the moment of my now famous genuflection, he shook my hand.
知道他低声对我说了什么吗？
Do you know what he said to me quietly?
“谢谢你，上校”
"Thank you, Colonel."
我问他谢我什么？谢我让他终生残废吗？
"For what?" I asked. "For laming you for the rest of your life?"
不，他谢我放他一条生路，这个懦夫…
No, but for making him understand, to see with his own eyes the swaggering...
也放他那些追随者一条生路
...the vile behaviour and perhaps worse of his dubious adherents.
不好意思，上校…
Please excuse me, dear Colonel.
您不觉得您所说的有点风马牛不相及吗？
Don't you think your bows and compliments overdid things a bit?
当然不会
No. Certainly no.
你真应该看看那位可怜的伟人…
You should have seen him, that poor, great man...
从栗树下大步走远，身上伤痕累累…
...lying under a chestnut tree, suffering in his body...
但内心伤得更深
...but even more in his spirit. Pitiful.
登陆西西里时，他不是再次说…
Didn't he say himself, when landing again in Sicily:
“我们朝着未知的方向进军”
"We are going towards the unknown."
这话让人不感动都难…
It was difficult to resist emotion.
况且，我有什么理由不感动呢？
Besides, why should I have resisted?
我只亲吻女士的手
I kiss the hand of ladies only.
即便在当时，殿下，我亲吻了一位女士的手…
But then, Prince, I also kissed the hand of the salvation of the kingdom...
我们士兵都很敬佩她的救国热情
...which is also a lady to whom we military men must pay homage.
帝亚哥，我失陪一下
I ask your pardon. Diego, excuse me.
一星期三场舞会实在太频繁了
Three balls in one week, it's too much.
我恨不得快点结束，不知道大家是否都开心
I can't wait for it to end. I can't think why everybody is so merry.
把发夹给我
Give me a hairpin.
真麻烦
How boring.
要是有人不断发出邀请，我们就得一直住在这里
Until we've finished with all these invitations, we must stay in the city.
我迫不及待想回到圣罗伦佐的家，过我们的平静生活
I can't wait to return to our villa at San Lorenzo, to our quiet life.
胡说，我希望舞会永远都不会结束
What are you saying? I'd like this ball to go on for ever, it's lovely.
不知道特帕斯的舞会是怎样的
What will the Trabias' ball be like?
我预订了一件绿色长裙，浅绿色的
I've ordered a green dress. Bright green.
你开心吗？
How about you?
我太开心了，塔克罗迪像个天使，你们对我都很好
I'm so happy. Tancredi is so sweet. You are all so sweet to me.
希望你能开心一点
I wish you were happier.
我能怎么样？我从不喜欢参加社交活动
What can I do about it? I've never liked being among people.
我也不喜欢跳舞，我跳得不好
I don't even like dancing. I've never been able to dance well.
那要看跟谁跳，找一个喜欢的舞伴
It depends on your partner. Find a partner you like.
我没兴趣
No, I'm not interested.
你知道有多少男人想得到你的青睐？
Do you know how many young men would be happy to court you?
你全都拒绝了
You discourage them all.
就像可怜的加里亚吉，记得吗？
Like poor Cavriaghi, remember?
你是怎么对他的！
How you treated him, poor man.
原来你在这儿，我到处都找不到你
There you are. I couldn't find you anywhere.
我们在打扮，你去哪儿了？我转过头你就不见了
We're tidying ourselves. Anyway, I couldn't find you, you had vanished.
我去听巴勒维西诺上校说话
I went to hear what the Colonel was saying.
他不是天才，不过说话很有道理
He's no genius, but he says many very sensible things.
他说得对，新政府需要法律和规则
It's true, the new kingdom needs order, legality, laws.
任何无政府企图都要压制
It needs to stifle, first of all...
不能允许冒险和动乱再次出现…
...any attempts at anarchy. No more adventures or disorders.
哪怕是采取残酷苛刻的手段…
Even if that entails severe or painful methods...
例如枪杀与加里波第逃走的狂热分子
...like shooting those hotheads who deserted to go back with Garibaldi.
你认为他们会遭到枪杀？
Do you think they'll shoot them?
你不知道？今天一早他们就成了逃亡分子
Didn't you know? This morning at dawn. And it's right. They were deserters.
你不该这样说
You would not have spoken like that once.
你错了，亲爱的
My dear, you are mistaken.
我一直都这样说话
I've always spoken like this.
总之，你不会明白
Therefore, these are things you cannot understand.
等等，康塞塔
Concetta, wait.
让我走！
Let me go!
我很明白
I think I understand very well.
我仍然觉得你不该那样说，我受够了
I said you wouldn't have spoken like that once. That's enough for me.
她很可爱，尤其是生气时
She's so sweet, especially when she becomes angry.
可怜的康塞塔，她还爱着你
Poor Concetta. The truth is, she's still in love with you.
☆那你呢，还爱着我吗？★当然
☆And are you still in love with me?★Yes.
看到萨利纳王子了吗？
Have you seen the Prince of Salina?
卡洛吉罗，是时候告辞了，整理一下衣服
Don Calogero, it's time to go. Pull yourself together.
请给我杯热咖啡
Coffee, please. Hot coffee.
谢谢你们今晚的款待
Thank you for this unforgettable evening.
你们真要走了吗？
Must you go already?
我们要直接回军营，这是军队作风
We're going straight to the barracks, as tradition demands of us soldiers.
是我们的职责
Our duty obliges us.
而且，夜间工作还未结束
Moreover, our tasks for this night are not yet over.
清理一下，把蜡烛吹灭
Tidy up a little and extinguish the candles.
玛格丽特，谢谢你们今晚的款待
Dear Margherita, thank you so much for the wonderful evening. Magnificent.
你原来在这儿呢，舅妈到处找你
There you are. Aunt is looking for you everywhere.
那几个姑娘要走了
Angelica, Concetta and Carolina are ready to leave.
能帮我个忙吗？我已经跟主人告别了
Can you do me a favour, my boy? I've already said my farewells.
帮你舅妈叫辆马车，我走路回去
Will you call the carriage for your aunt? I'm walking back.
☆这么晚走路回去？★我想呼吸些新鲜空气
☆Walking? At this hour?★I need some air.
你是不是不舒服？
Don't you feel well?
头有点痛，透透气就没事
A slight headache. Fresh air will help.
一切都很顺利吧？
Everything went very well, don't you think?
好极了，舅舅，很快就会有好消息给你
Marvellously, uncle. You know, I'll soon have some good news for you.
我跟宾佐尼谈了谈，下次选举…
I just spoke to Finzori. It seems that at the next elections...
你会成为候选人
You'll be the candidate.
你已经知道了？
You knew about it?
失陪一下
Excuse me for a moment.
虔诚的星星…
O star, O faithful star!
何时我才能远离尘世间的一切…
When will you decide to give me a less fleeting appointment...
在永恒不变的世界中得到永生？
...far from everything, in your realm of perennial certainty?
优良部队，有军队就会有商业
An excellent army. They do things properly.
所有这一切…
Just what we needed...
就是西西里所需要的
...for Sicily.
现在我们能好好休息了
Now we can take it easy.